{
  "reference_number": "11773",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "I object to this limited set. Use of the word 'net' (allowing offsets) and omission of the word methane (using short-lived gasses)\n makes this question pretty disingenuous. No option here actually allows for Methane to be reduced. Methane impact cannot be\n\n ignored or side-tracked !! Just offsetting methane emissions and carrying on with the agricultural practice (option 3) is dangerous!! It\n is HALF our GHG emissions - this is HUGE deal. Failure to be clear on surveying for an opinion here is a weakness of this public\n\n consultation. I fear that many will be mislead by deliberate structure of this question - which seems to intentionally duck the most\n pressing issue alongside timeline - Q/ is 2050 aggressive enough? A - NO - I have checked option 2 because it caps the growth of\n emissions from cattle. There is no option here to insist on an actual reduction of emissions from cattle. There is no question here on\n\n the aggressiveness of the timeline for change."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Reliability, audit and integrity of international off-shore carbon sequestration programmes has a long way to go to be TRUSTWORTHY\n as an offset for NZ carbon emitting activity. Keep it onshore until things improve. Set policy to stimulate the domestic afforrestary\n business in New Zealand and compete, rather than enable NZ business to give it away thro' purchase of offshore carbon units."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The only acceptable revision would be to make it more aggressive a timeline to net zero GHG emissions. This Act is and should\n remain apolitical, target softening is not an option."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Softening targets in any way (such as stratification) is a failure to grasp the magnitude of the global risk and the local impacts that will\n\n follow. Set the targets and leave them alone."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Softening targets in any way (such as stratification) is a failure to grasp the magnitude of the global risk and the local impacts that will\nfollow. Set the targets and leave them alone."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Softening targets in any way (such as stratification) is a failure to grasp the magnitude of the global risk and the local impacts that will\n\nfollow. Set the targets and leave them alone."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely necessary - urgency is in fact important, this is not often the case but is undeniable for the carbon act."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Imperative that the critical inclusion of agriculture (specifically dairy) emissions is NOT AVOIDED. Over 50% of our national GHG\n\nemissions are methane. The sector therefore MUST adapt to be part of the transition to a low-carbon economy. Failure to include and\naddress this enormous driver of GHG generation in the New Zealand will make a mockery of the Carbon Act, and will represent gross\n\ndis-service to future generations, my children included. It is imperative that the Act delivers on this, because it is morally and ethically\nthe right thing to do - regardless of political and economic optics."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Use a risk based approach to monitoring - where government oversight is applied to areas with the highest risk of failure to comply\nwith climate goals, coupled to the severity of the risk to climate by non-compliance. Where the drivers to change are weakest,\n\nrequires most policing by central agencies."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "The NZ ETS has already been mis-handled and become totally ineffective, handing back ETS policy settings to any elected official is a\nmistake. History tell us that the scheme is easily undermined by flip flopping on ETS policy settings. Green washing is the biggest risk\n\nwe face, hence any ETS should enable just a small fraction of our commitments. Science and the balance of risk/impact should guide\nthe degree to which the country should rely upon an ETS mechanism. History tells us we should not rely upon a NZ government to\n\nget the policy settings right, so it becomes an inherently less reliable a choice for the future of the country."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Mitigation MUST come first - an adaptation bill/act can follow - if it compromises the speed of getting good legislation on a net\n\nreduction of GHG emissions passed into law then it should not be included in the Carbon Act. Adaptation is consequential, the\ndegree to which this becomes material depends on the success or failure of efforts to mitigate. Make the main thing the main thing\nand keep the momentum."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Adaptation should not be the focus of the act - bias should be heavily to MITIGATION"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Adaptation should not be the focus of the act - bias should be heavily to MITIGATION"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "METHANE The majority of the 16 questions here concern the proposed climate change commission and how far its powers should\n\nextend. This balance is disturbing. The most contentious question refers to the definition of what “zero carbon” actually means.\nEvery option indicates a 'net' emission number, signalling that offsets are acceptable. Two scenarios cover all types of GHG which\n\ninclude methane. Neither allow for the actual reduction of methane. One would allow its growth with offsets, the other would call for\nstabilisation of the methane emissions. The question is devious and this is deeply concerning. Without good knowledge the intent of\nsubmissions here can easily be watered down and/or lost. This looks deliberate. Methane cannot be ignored. It cannot be merely\n\noffset, then carrying on with the current practice of cattle/sheep agriculture at scale. Methane It is HALF the problem in NZ and hence\nHALF the solution must lie here. Methane emissions need to be cut hard and fast, not stabilised at their present levels, and ducking\n\nthis issue will be a disaster for the credibility of the ruling NZ government. As a secondary issue the questions on this topic should\nhave been transparent and not coded so as to apparently side track the issue. The MAIN issue for New Zealand. OPPORTUNITY NZ\n\nshould set an important precedent. New Zealand should become the first country in the world to put a price on agricultural\nemissions, academics and published authors and corporates have already done so, nation states are the laggards. Ethically speaking\n\nNew Zealand can and should lead the way and MUST include ACTUAL REDUCTIONS in agricultural emissions. LACKS AMBITION The\ntarget date of 2050 for attaining this is woefully inadequate given the risks posed. 2035 seems much more impactful and urgent\ntimeline for humanity to act decisively given that we are collectively running the risk for our children of catastrophic climate change…"
    }
  ]
}
